<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: trip | Andy Czerwonka]]></title>
  <link href="http://andyczerwonka.com/blog/categories/trip/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andyczerwonka.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-09T13:02:41-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://andyczerwonka.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andy Czerwonka]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes three are better than one]]></title>
    <link href="http://andyczerwonka.com/blog/2013/07/07/sometimes-three-are-better-than-one/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-07T20:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://andyczerwonka.com/blog/2013/07/07/sometimes-three-are-better-than-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm in Katowice, Poland on a business trip for a few days that straddle a weekend, so we decided to head out to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zakopane">Zakopane</a>, the popular mountain town in southern Poland. Knowing we were in for a day of driving, we headed to the gas station.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-vOCz3yzV6bI/Udp-YIUkYDI/AAAAAAAAFVc/2By_6bxsftc/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1269.JPG"></p>

<p>Wow! Gas is expensive... basically double of what we're used to complaining about in Calgary. No wonder people don't drive around here unless they have to. While we might take it for granted, I'll bet it's a significant part of the average family budget when thinking about long drives.</p>

<p>About an hour into our trip the weather progressively got worse by the minute. By the time we arrived it was raining so hard we needed to pull over and figure out our next move given we didn't prepare for the rain.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/--csVWrFmPsA/Udp9Ip1VdDI/AAAAAAAAFU4/9CMZGppsu-Y/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1278.JPG"></p>

<p>We found a little shop that sold cheap rain jackets for a couple of złoty. Given the amount of people walking around, it's no atypical to get this much rain. Armed with protection from the elements we walked up and down Krupówki (the main <a href="http://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulica_Krup%C3%B3wki_w_Zakopanem">deptak</a> in Zakopane) for a couple of hours. It was really interesting to see the different types of street food, especially <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oscypek">Oscypek</a>, the heavily smoked sheep's milk cheese that is grilled and typically served with a sweet-berry compote.</p>

<p>All-in-all Krupówki was a fun place to hang out. After lunch we decided to head out given we wanted to see a few more places before heading back to Katowice. On the way out of town we drove past <a href="http://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanktuarium_Matki_Bo%C5%BCej_Fatimskiej_w_Zakopanem">Sanktuarium Matki Bożej Fatimskiej</a>, a sanctuary that was consecrated by Pope John Paul II in 1981. Given the amount of attention it was getting from other tourists, we decided to loop back and have a look.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Pvuv6dnqhRY/UdqCElcNkPI/AAAAAAAAFX8/qjwJEeWDE3Y/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1280.JPG"></p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-L3sufWPZBLs/UdqCSImGCgI/AAAAAAAAFXs/KXoib6GOp8w/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1292.JPG"></p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-yscJUvRPeaw/UdqEVH798DI/AAAAAAAAFY0/tATuysBQKfI/w1166-h328-no/DSCF1296.JPG"></p>

<p>After an hour of walking around these serene grounds, off to Slovakia!</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-MoZamA-6m90/Udp7K-ijAuI/AAAAAAAAFUk/URlP9veVmuM/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1312.JPG"></p>

<p>I'm not sure why we decided to head this far south, but why not? It's another country I can knock off my list. :-)</p>

<p>Our brief encounter with Slovakia through gave me a tiny glimpse of what seemed to be a much quieter life when compared to Poland. Not many people in the streets. People just doing their thing. What was slightly alarming was that even though the main highway (or should I say <em>side street</em>) ran right through the middle of their town, people were ignorant of the fact that cars were whizzing by at 80 km/hr. It didn't seem to phase anyone or anything. People continued to walk down the road with kids, dogs, chickens, cows, etc. Correct... we saw a lady walking her cow down the street. Awesome. I missed that shot.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-e81e2R3DOmg/UdqIjNZypXI/AAAAAAAAFcM/IPfa-EcElVA/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1319.JPG"></p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-nO5idNPUgmw/UdqIjOQ3SuI/AAAAAAAAFbU/MHjKTJLYLSE/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1321.JPG"></p>

<p>I don't remember when we passed from Slovakia into the Czech Republic. Nothing seemed to change. The roadway's are lined with homes, stores, cemeteries, lakes, farms and even a golf course. This is beautiful country.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-9BGoQCg3Icc/UdqKdPja4nI/AAAAAAAAFco/QwPgA7Nfq18/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1334.JPG"></p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-xmp1LTqHYfU/UdqV2Z8cczI/AAAAAAAAFhs/P7wLyXGlgxM/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1473.JPG"></p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-OrNoib8STWA/Udqbu6Ry0tI/AAAAAAAAFkQ/ektSh7R7YrI/w1167-h775-no/photo.jpg"></p>

<p>Because we didn't get a chance to stop at the Czech-Polish border for a few pictures, we decided that the final leg out our tour before heading back to Katowice was going to be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cieszyn">Cieszyn</a>, and small town that straddles both Poland and the Czech Republic. I wanted to get a couple of border shots so I could officially document my trip.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-5sOr0qPM_lA/UdqYnIPA5HI/AAAAAAAAFik/bZRD0c-YoNM/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1482.JPG"></p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Ktsx7Ziv97M/UdqY3B36nOI/AAAAAAAAFi0/e40VVN0e_zg/w1167-h775-no/DSCF1492.JPG"></p>

<p>With evidence in hand, we headed back to Katowice. When I left Calgary I thought a trip to one country was enough, but sometimes three are better than one.</p>

<p>Feel free to browse through <a href="https://plus.google.com/photos/106813386163068618139/albums/5898162083868783985?authkey=CKCb8LWVt-bkNQ">all the pictures from today's trip</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
